Hello, welcome everyone. It is
>> You want me to start right? Oh,
>> can I go now?
>> You can.
>> Yeah. Right.
>> All right.
>> Okay. Hi, this is R Wen here presenting
a second live stream about this unified
theory of language um which is described
in an archive preprint which you can see
at that address. So this is the second
live stream in the first um and this is
a slide I showed the first time around
about the various bits of language which
are studied phenology syntax semantics
pragmatics learning and evolution and
the two bold ones pragmatics how we
converse and evolution how language
evolved those are the bits we're going
to focus on this time and um I should
say that these two columns
listener uh put in there just to remind
us that uh you have to for all of these
problems you have to
pay attention to both how the speaker
goes about it and how the listener goes
about it and I'll try and do that while
we're um going through this. So um just
a few key points from part one of the
live stream. Um and these are the points
most relevant to this this second part.
I said the language is hierarchical
basin pattern matching which is very
much in the in line with the FE and so
you could have an FP implementation
language if you like although that
hasn't been done to my knowledge. Um the
approach I'll be taking here is ch from
cognitive linguistics or what's also
called construction grammars. It's not a
chkin approach and in cognitive
linguistics there are thousands of
patterns
uh in active in language and in fact
there's at least one pattern for every
word in a language. So having thousands
of patterns and cognitive linguistics
has produced working models of phology,
syntax, semantics and language learning.
It hasn't done so much about pragmatics.
Generally the study of pragmatics has
lagged long behind the study of the
other subjects like semantics and
syntax.
So in cognitive linguistics every word
is represented by a con what they call a
construction that is a feature structure
which is a directed as cyclic graph
structure and I showed some examples of
these
and the key operation in language in
these uh construction based grammarss is
unification and I showed that
unification is a form of basian pattern
matching. So that's the key points from
the first live stream. What this live
stream is going to be about is mainly
about pragmatics and evolution said I
should start by saying language long ago
started in conversation and we had
conversations before we had syntax and
semantics. Language evolved by sexual
selection for the display of
intelligence. That's how language got
started.
And because of that language is a biased
thing. Language is not as some people
imagine a kind of neutral format for
talking about reality. It's actually
biased to be all about social status and
I'll try and illustrate that. Now coming
back to pragmatic conversation.
Conversation requires mind reading.
That's the essential requirement to
carry on a conversation.
And then I shall present a model of
pragmatic model of conversations which
is built on basian pattern matching just
like the syntax and semantics we talked
about in the last live stream. And so
the basis of this is do we learn mind
reading patterns
and in those mind breathing patterns we
often when we're thinking we often have
what I call a shadow audience which
we're trying to work out what the shadow
audience will think about what we say
and what we do. So that shadow audience
is a kind of something we imagine which
assesses our own status and the shadow
audience is the basis of the human self.
Um and so the shadow or is very
important because it's the basis of all
human self is the basis of all societies
how we collaborate
but also it has a dark side and that
uh is
I shall describe the main affliction of
mankind
and finally I shall talk a little about
mindfulness which is a release from the
human self and the shadow audience. So
that's the main topic I'm going to
discuss in this live stream. Let's
get straight into it. Um, language
started in conversation. Imagine about a
million years ago before we had
semantics or syntax, we started to
converse with each other. The semantics
part of it was by mimicking, by gesture,
and by pointing. You point to things and
draw attention to them and so on. And
for all conversation between two people,
there has to be a common ground of
shared understanding between those two
people.
And so a conversation starts with two
people both understanding something
about their current situation. And each
turn in the conversation, one person
then another person. Each turn adds some
facts to the common ground. And some of
these facts are about the mental states
of the speakers. And I shall illustrate
this in a minute. So because of that
conversation requires mind reading.
requires each person to infer things
about the other person's mental state
and that we do by basing pattern
matching.
And so a very important part of
pragmatics is the study of speech acts
and speech acts are ways in which one
party in a conversation adds facts about
his own mental state to the common
ground.
And just to give an example of this, a
very early conversation say a million
years ago between two people A and B. Uh
and they have a certain common ground.
The red points in before the
conversation starts. The common ground
is that the time is the afternoon. A is
a man who's just been hunting. B is a
son. There's a fire that they can both
see. And there is some meat because a
brought it back from hunting. And they
both have some general knowledge about
the world. They both know that to eat
some meat you have to cook it. So that
stuff above the dash line is the common
ground at the start and the conversation
between them I shall is illustrated by
these points here which each adds to the
common ground. So A says eat and he
points to something and so he's offering
that B might eat something. That's an
offer speech [snorts] act.
B says yes. And so B accepts the offer
of A.
And then B says you cook. And B wants to
know who's going to do the cooking. So B
wants be a state in which B knows who is
going to do the cooking. So you can see
here we're building up facts about both
parties mental states. A says yes. So
that
adds the fact A is going to do the
cooking. So those are the facts which
are explicitly added to the common
ground. There are other acts other facts
which can be deduced from that because
they're in the common ground. B knows
that A is going to do the cooking and A
knows that B knows that A is going to
do. So there are loads of mental state
facts in the common ground
and the conversation proceeds by speech
acts which of different kinds like
offers and questions and answers and so
on which adds of common ground. So
that's the basic model of a
conversation. How conversations started
a long time ago before we had elaborate
syntax or semantics before most of
language.
So in this picture semantics came about
by making speech acts more fine grain.
There are a few broad types of speech
act which are declarations where you say
something and offer a request or a
command or a question and so on and each
speech act adds some fact about your own
mental state to the common ground. Now
semantics is how we develop language to
allow speech acts to be more fine
grained. They can be about certain
agents or acts or patients. They can be
at different times or different
attitudes to them and so on. So that's
how semantics came about and syntax
[clears throat] is just the structured
language we need to convey semantics. So
in this picture syntax and and semantics
came out of pragmatic. Pragmatic came
first. Now that interestingly is quite
the reverse of the order in which
language has been traditionally studied.
There's been a long-term study of syntax
and semantics starting way back when and
pragmatics has always been a kind of
poor relation that came later.
But in this picture, pragmatics actually
came first.
So what is pragmatics? It's studied
under a number of headings and these on
the left hand side are traditional
headings under which we studied
pragmatics
speech and here are some examples of
them. Here are some speech acts of
greeting. Hello. There's a request. Can
you pass us all? And the same sort of
structure, but a very different thing.
It's a question. Can you p vault? In
other words, this wants the listener to
do something and this wants the listener
to just provide some information. And
here's an answer. No.
Reference re resolution is sometimes
called dexis. In other words, we're
always using noun phrases, nouns,
referring to things. We have to work out
what thing precisely is being referred
to. So, you can use the word him.
Somebody's got to work out what him
refers to. Or you say, talk about the
blue one near the back. Somebody has to
work out what that is. Now, there are a
couple of topics which are commonly
studied which are quite closely related.
Presupposition and implicature. Both of
them you you're actually beyond the
obvious thing that you're saying there's
something else added to the conversation
to the common ground. Presupposition is
when what you say something it
presupposes something else. You say my
cat's not hungry that presupposes you
got a cat. When you say he regrets going
to Spain that kind of pre presupposes he
actually did go to Spain. Implicature is
an implication of what you say. You say,
"Shall we ask him, oh, he's got an essay
to write and and the listener has to
work out. That means he can't come
along." Or if you say, "I caught some of
the geese." You're somehow implying that
you didn't catch all of the geese. So
those are presupposition intricacy. Then
there are other topics like irony where
you say, "Yeah, sure." Or, "That's
really brilliant." or hyperbole, you
exaggerate, you're a genius. Or
metaphor, where you say, "She's a
brick." In other words, she's a very
reliable person. Or you say, "He's a
chocolate teapot." And you're saying the
opposite. He's an unreliable person. So
those are some of the the subjects
in pragmatics.
And the model of pragmatics has to give
some account of all of them. And you can
see if you look at them, look at each
example, there is the common ground
features in how you work out what's
going on and mind readading features as
well. So
what I've developed recently is a basian
model of pragmatics and I'll just try
and describe in outline how it works. So
both people in their heads have a
version of the common ground. They start
with a shared understanding of what's
going on and each fact in the common
ground has a think I call pro which I
call prominent
uh a very prominent fact is the most
recent thing added to the common ground
as well as a basian probability
and if you some facts you can infer from
other facts generally the inferred facts
are less prominent than the things
they're inferred from. So in this model
there are pragmatic constructions which
are just like the word constructions of
syntax and semantics that I talked about
last time.
[snorts] So facts in the seat the common
ground are created by unifying various
things together. The sound of the
utterances that you hear or are going to
speak pragmatic instructions and and
prior facts in the common ground. These
unifications are always done in an order
prominence first until you get a good
enough result and unification as I said
last time is basian pattern matching.
So pragmatic constructions are just like
the other constructions of of language
like word constructions. They have a
phonetic pole which includes the sound
part and a semantic pole and may include
other things as well and a semantic pole
which includes only the meaning. So what
happens in a conversation is that the
speaker and the listener unifies the
same pragmatic construction. The
speakers unify in one direction from the
semantic pole to the phonetic pole and
listeners go in the opposite direction.
They hear sound. So they go from the
phonetic pole to the semantic pole. So
this is a version of both how the
speakers work out what to say and how
the listeners work out what they mean.
And as a result of this in the model you
can show how both versions of the common
ground the speaker's version and the
listener's version stay in step. And so
this is a model in which semantics comes
out of the pragmatics.
Now this model of pragmatics is
different from the way pragmatics has
been studied in the past. Previous work
on pragmatics has been in two different
schools. this so-called Neogian school
which is named after the philosopher
Paul Grace who really started the study
of pragmatics in about 1960s
and the names associated with the neocin
school are horn and Steven Levenson and
various others and the other school of
pragmatics is called relevance theory
which is started by Dan Berber and I de
Wilson
now both of Those schools take the
traditional view that semantics comes
first and the the mind the listener or
the speaker does a bunch of semantics
first and then chuck chucks the result
over the wall if you like to a pragmatic
inference part of the brain.
And both schools
place all their emphasis
on the work has to be done by the
listener to understand what he hears.
And they both practically ignore the
problem of the work done by the speaker
to work out what to say next to be
understood. So they're very lopsided.
The other thing about those models is
they describe the pragmatic inference in
words in verbal descriptions. They don't
have really working models. So the
advantages of this approach over
previous approaches is there's no fixed
boundary between pragmatic and
semantics. Two are intermingled all the
way.
Is it a joint model solves both sides of
the problem? The speaker's problem and
the listener problem. And it's a a
continuous extension of the basian model
that I described in the last live
stream. And it's it's extension of
cognitive linguistics.
And the final advantage is it works and
it works fast because one thing about
conversations is that we can respond in
conversation very fast.
And there's a puzzle about how we do all
the inferences we required so rapidly.
In this model, the the inferences are
done preconciously by basin pattern
matching just by like so many other
things in the mind.
Right? So there's the model of
pragmatics.
Um I shall now skip to a different
subject to come back to pragmatic later.
How did language evolve? I discussed
this to a certain extent in the last
live stream and in the the first live
stream I said language uses hierarchal
basian pattern matching like so many
things in the brain and this talk
addresses part two how did language
evolve particularly in mankind and in no
other species.
So that is the next few slides.
I shall first talk about natural
selection and sexual selection.
As we well know to pass on your genes uh
you need to do two things. You need to
survive until you're an adult and you
can reproduce and you need to find a
mate in order to reproduce. So these are
really different kinds of pressures
and they lead respectively to natural
selection how you survive to adulthood
and sexual selection how you find a
mate. Now sexual selection is a very
common force in nature.
It leads to the kind of displays that we
see in flowers and birds plumage and all
sorts of things leads to the diversity
of species on the planet and it leads to
sexual dimmorphism the differences
between males and females.
So if I say language involved evolution
involved sexual selection that's really
not a remarkable thing to say. It would
be much more remarkable
if sexual selection was not involved in
the evolution of language. So the
hypothesis is which I publish in
frontier's journal that language evol
sorry I'll talk a little more about how
sexual selection works first.
Natural selection is a gradual
adaptation to the habitat. So it's a
hill climbing process and optimization
process.
Sexual selection is very different. The
maths of spec sexual selection been
worked out about 1980 by Lande and by
John Maidan Smith. And the maths is a
positive feedback process. Positive
feedback between genes in the male and
genes in the female.
And the results of sexual of this
mathematical model which agree with the
data are
sexual selection leads to novel and
vivid traits like the peacock's tail
shown here. Fast visible changes of
phenotype. Again the peacock's tail is
very visible because it has to be
visible to it has to help find a mate.
And the results of sexual selection are
always unique to one species. The
peacock's completely different from any
other species of birds.
Results of sexual section always
exaggerated, strongly exaggerated beyond
what is most fit. So the peacock's tail
obviously is a big handicap for the male
peacock, but it needs that to get a
mate. So the final point is they
handicap. So these are the results of
sexual selection. Novel fast changes
unique to a species exaggerated and
handicaps.
So here's the hypothesis which I
published about a couple of years ago in
frontiers
that language evolved by sexual
selection particularly to display
intelligence. In order to get a mate we
have to show off our intelligence
and that as I say is a very unremarkable
hypothesis but it does answer the big
questions of language evolution. So here
are some of the questions and the
answers. Why do we have such ludicrously
large brains? The answer is there is
sexual selection. To display
intelligence and to display
intelligence, you obviously have to have
it.
Why language? Why do we display
intelligence by language? Because words
is a very quick and efficient way to
show off our intelligence.
Why is language so amazingly fast and
expressive? In fact, it's much faster
than we would need in any natural
habitat for any natural purpose like
arranging hunts or arranging gathering
or whatever planning a camp.
Language can say things in a few seconds
whereas for practical purposes you might
be able to take a few minutes. And
language is so fast because sexual
selection causes exaggerated traits. The
speed of language has been exaggerated
beyond the biological need.
A big question about language evolution
is why do closely related species,
particularly chimps, not have language
like ours? They're so different. And the
answer is simply sexual selection is
unique to a species. It's not a habitat
uh selection pressure. It's a species
internal selection pressure.
And the final question, why do we have
language when the benefits of language
don't match the huge costs of our extra
brain and our large brain 20% extra food
requirement and the answer is sexual
selection causes handicaps. So all in
all it seems very likely that language
did evolve in this process by sexual
selection and it is a tool
for doing practical things. We do
practical things with it. Primarily,
it's a tool for showing off our
intelligence.
Now, intelligence is related to social
space status. We show off our
intelligence using language as a way to
get mate. But getting a mate also
requires high status in the social
group.
So when we're using language, we're
always very concerned about our own
social status.
And what this means is that when we're
doing conversation using these pragmatic
mind reading patterns, we use those
patterns to infer not only what the
other person knows about the world in
general, but what they think about us.
In other words, in a conversation, we're
always asking the question ourselves
questions like, "Will he think I'm
impolite? Will she think I'm being
uncaring?" And these are all to do with
our social status.
So, this is a very powerful preconscious
filter of what we say.
In other words, we often ask these
questions. We say, "No, I better not say
that." But it's done very quickly
because there's a famous result from
Leven Terrera that people take turns in
conversations within a fifth of a second
of the other person stopping. They work
these things out very rapidly and they
the way they work them out rapidly is by
preconcious basian pattern matching. We
with these so-called status patterns and
we have hundreds of those status
patterns. If I say this, they will think
I'm good or bad to maybe.
So intelligence, showing off
intelligence in language is very closely
related to maintaining our social
status.
Language is about social status. We can
see that not from the evolution of
language but from the present day
properties of what language looks like.
Now we can take various aspects of
language and show how they are relevant
to status. The most basic aspect of
language is that the structure of a
sentence agent act patient or agent act.
And this kind of implies that the agent
has chosen to do something. The agent
has exercised some free will and will be
judged by the results of those actions.
The contrast with animals is animals of
course have no free will. They just do
what the moment requires. So animals
don't make choices.
Language obviously has future tense and
past tense. And why was that introduced?
Because people's status can be judged
not only by what they're doing now, but
what they did in the past and what they
will do in the future.
And again, there's a big contrast with
the animals that we evolved from.
Animals just live in the present. I
think their minds have little or no use
for future episodes or past episodes.
So animals would not be able to use the
future or past tense.
Possession language has words like mine,
your and so on. They're introduced
because possession is control and
control has status implications. If I've
got a fast car that
uh if it's mine, then that increases my
status. Some people think animals of
course don't have possessions.
There are modal verbs in language. Verbs
like can and should and would and so on.
Can implies that you've cho that you can
choose to do things or not to do things.
Should implies society thinks you ought
to do it. It's a good action. So both
those all those modal verbs are laden
with status implications.
Whereas animals don't choose what to do
and they don't modal verbs are not
relevant to them. Can't say an animal
can do this. Animal either does this or
it doesn't do that.
We have mental state verbs. Knows and
wants and intends. Again, states of mind
are very very relevant to status.
Somebody has bad intentions. That's a
low status thing to be.
Language has comparisons, bigger,
better, and so on. Comparison is
relevant to social rank ranking. In
other words,
bigger and so on is always putting
people on in order of social ranking. So
language is absolutely soaked with
features which are all to do with social
status. is not neutral. And with every
utterance, we preconciously infer what
it implies about our own status in the
eyes of other people using these learned
status patterns.
And that brings me on to an important
topic called the shadow audience.
When we talk to some somebody, we're
preconciously inferring what that person
will think about us. We're matching
these status patterns to filter what we
say. But when we're on our own privately
thinking, that evolved as a rehearsal of
what we're going to say. That's thinking
is rehearsing what we might say to
somebody. And we rehearse in order to
make it more impressive.
But when you're privately thinking,
there is no real audience there. So what
we do is we invent shadow audiences,
people we know who we imagine how they
will judge what we say. They could be
parents or friends or or just people in
general. We use these status patterns
that we learned in conversation to infer
what the shadow audience is going to
think of us. And this is a very
important part of our thought process.
It's going on the whole time and it
makes us feel emotional reaction. In
other words, if I think this is going to
make me look bad, I start to feel bad.
And so the shadow audience is actually
what creates the human idea of myself.
That's the agent self. That's the myself
who's going to act and who's going to be
judged by other people on the basis of
what I say and do.
So the shadow audience is the thing that
really creates the human sense of self
which is much more elaborate and complex
than any animal's sense of itself.
So with that in mind, we can consider
how thoughts work in fractions of a
second.
And there you are thinking, hearing the
words in your mind. And you may be
hearing about two or two, three or four
words every second.
And so your brain is doing some very
fast preconcious pattern matching. It's
matching
two to four word patterns per second
just to make up the sentence. And it's
matching those status patterns as well
to think what will people think of me.
And the status patterns make you feel
emotions.
And what happens when you feel an
emotion is that bodily feeling may match
some further status patterns
to cascades of status patterns. And this
is all happening faster than conscious
thought. So that's why we feel such
irrational and unpredictable emotions
sometimes. And it comes to the quote
from Bla Pascal.
The heart has its own reason which
reason doesn't understand because it's
happening faster than conscious
reasoning.
So this leads to what I call the dark
side of language. These learned status
patterns are part of language and they
enable us to cooperate cooperate with
each other as members of society.
So this is what has underpinned the
whole of human progress while we conquer
the planet. But these status patterns do
have a dark side.
We are constantly feeling anxious that
we should be doing better
and we have this idea of myself as other
other people think about me. But it's a
secondhand idea. It's not what I think
of me, it's what I think other people
think. And it's a flawed idea because
the patterns we use aren't perfect.
They're very inaccurate sometimes.
So, we are constantly looking at our own
life history to
polish it and refine [clears throat] it
to preserve our self-esteem. We feel
these emotions in chaotic ways. And to
keep our shadow audiences happy, we
agree with what we think they're going
to think. In other words,
um we don't think for ourselves. We
think what would the group think about
this? That's group think.
And the second part of that is to
enhance our own status. We have out
groups. We have other people who we in
other groups who we diminish them and
and we diminish their status. So this is
what leads to tribalism and intolerance.
So the dark side of language is the root
of human affliction and evil. It's uh
produced some great things in society
and civilization but some very bad
things which we're all aware of.
So next I come to the topic of
meditation and mindfulness.
Recapping
what I've uh said before, the human
agent self, the self which acts and
which is judged by other people is
learned in language in these status
patterns.
Now I believe that mindful states are
states in which that agent self is
diminished or absence and this agrees
very well with the phenomenal reports of
what it's like to be in my mindful
state. And there's a very good
collection of these phenomenal reports
in a book by Metsinger called the
elephant in the line. And we can go
through these reports of what mindful
states are like in Messenger and we can
interpret them in terms of the
hypothesis that it's all about language
status patterns. So meditative states
are relaxed and peaceful and the reason
is that the anxiety and the cascades of
thought which the status patterns create
are reduced in meditative states.
There's a silence and non-reaction about
it. And when there's less language going
on there are few active status patterns
and even when thoughts arise they can be
just observed as thoughts about
reactions.
the sense of nonident identification, no
self, no physical boundaries and a
connectedness with other things.
And the interpretation here is that the
agent self is created by the status
bands and creates the boundary between
the self and the rest of the world. And
so that boundary gets dissolved.
There is a lot of compassion in
meditative states and the interpretation
is that when the agent self is not
protecting his own status, we are more
open to seeing what life is really like
for other people and seeing the world
from their point of view. In meditation,
there is no time. In deep meditation,
there's no time and there's no life
stories. Chronological time has been
created by language driven by status
concerns. And we build these life
stories to protect our own status. When
we're not concerned with our own status,
we're not concerned with life story.
There is a sense of clarity and what the
meditators call suchness in meditation.
And what this is is when we don't
classify things according to whether
they're good or bad for us, we can look
at them more closely and see what they
really are.
There's a sense in meditation sometimes
of nothing left to do. What that means
simply is that the agent self is not
present created by the status patterns.
There's no need for action.
There meditation is associ associated
with nonduality.
The duality between self and other is
brought about by language and when
language is less active there's less
duality.
So that is the correlation between
reports of what meditation is like and
the theory that it's really a lack of
language and the lack of the status
patterns that makes it like that.
So we can approach from another angle
some of the traditional things we know
about Buddhism. Many of aspects of
Buddhism we can interpret from this
point of view. The first noble truth of
Buddhism is duka suffering. But what
this is is continual discontent from the
action of status patterns saying we
should be doing better when they're
absent. Uh duka is absent.
The Buddhist cycle of birth and rebirth
is interesting. It doesn't mean we're
reincarnated physically literally
reborn. What it means is that the
there's an agent self which language is
created
and it recreates itself in cascades or
cycles.
The shadow audience creates the self and
the self creates this shadow audience.
So that cycle gets abolished.
Nirvana nana or nonduality is when that
cycle is no longer there
allowing the nondual experiencing self
to take to to be there.
Buddh often uses the word conditioning
that simply means the learning of status
patterns that we learned in language.
Uh the one flavor Zen Buddhism is
probably the most striden rejection of
language. Zen Buddhism says you can't
describe any of this in language at all.
So that interpretation of mindfulness
accords with long known uh teachings of
Buddhism.
Now here is a hypothesis about how we
learn my
we know from language that we never
unlearn a word. Once we've learned a
word we've got it for life really. So
how can if we've got these status
patterns and they're the problem how can
we unlearn them? can't unlearn the
status pattern. So how can we influence
reduce their influence on us?
Well, there is a way because basic band
matching is always competitive. It's
always several candidate patterns are
tried out and only the one that wins the
competition goes on to have an conscious
effect. The patterns that lose the
competition don't have conscious
effects.
So here's the hypothesis about how we
learn life.
status patterns. The status patterns
that drive our emotions are triggered by
feelings on our bodies. But when
meditating, we do is we observe those
bodily feelings as closely as we can.
And while we're doing that, as a side
effect, we learn some new patterns which
are called mindful patterns. And these
new bands say when you see when you feel
certain bodily feelings like something
you're breathing or something your
stomach or whatever it may be
simply pay closer attention to them.
Find out what they're like. So this is a
different pattern from the status
pattern. And so what happens is the
mindful patterns
compete against the status patterns and
win the competition. So the status
patterns are less influential when you
pay attention to the mindful patterns.
So mindful states happen when status
patterns are diminished or absent. So
there is a hypothesis about how
meditation is learned.
Um
now finally last slide really is a
switch of topic something that I've
postponed for some time but an important
aspect of language in all ways
every language consists of a very large
number of constructions word
constructions and status construction
and so on. Each one of them is like a
species and the whole language is like a
habitat or an ecology and one species
reproduces by being used and learned
passed on. So this is what happens.
People use a certain word children hear
it and they learn it they pass it on and
in that evolution. So that process
evolves constructions. Constructions
compete with each other, compete against
other constructions and they're very
strong selection pressures on the
construction in the language. They
should be have a useful meaning that
people actually need to speak them, need
to say them from time to time. They must
be brief enough if somebody can say
things quickly, they'll do it the other
way. They must be unambiguous enough and
they must be learnable. So the there are
selection pressures on constructions
on words and status
patterns which cause them to evolve.
They lead to very fast language change.
That's why language changes within a few
human generations.
And what that means is that much of the
structure we see in language is a result
of that fast evolution. And it's not the
evolution of the human brain that made
it. For instance, there are language
universals about the structure of
most languages. And they are telling us
how languages have evolved. What that
means is that language is actually
telling us less about the human brain
than we thought it did.
Okay. So that's the end of the second
live stream of the paired material. Um
there are various topics you might like
to discuss.
How mind reading patterns operate in
conversation. Whether language did
evolve by sexual selection.
How language is about status.
Status patterns use a shadow audience.
The human sense of self based on the
shadow audience being a rather
secondhand idea of ourselves.
Language and human affliction.
mindfulness and evolution of language
balance. So,
over for any questions.
>> Thank you, Robert.
There's a few things I wrote down and
then I think this is a great menu and
I'll also look in the live chat if
anyone writes a question. Okay, so
lot to think slash say in that uh
>> in that self-aware language. Nexus.
I was wondering what what could or would
address that shadow side of language? Is
that a feature of some of the
constraints of a given language like
reification of processes or objects or
um affixing adjectives
in in some way that uh somehow
disrespects
the onlogical
aspects of of properties of systems. Or
is it like any symbolic
machine or any symbolic approximation is
going to have a shadow
or to to what to what is the alternative
or is it that shadow is
is a necessary
follow
uh it's a consequence of proposing
symbolic representation of the
ecological scenario. IO.
>> Well, I think it came very early on. In
other words, we had shadow audiences
before we had much semantics, before we
had much syntax, before we had much
symbolic systems. You go back to the
very early conversations.
Um, let me just go right back.
um
conversation before people had many
words. They just used pointing and took
turns in conversation. I think the
shadow I think even then
people had real conversations in which
they imagined what the other person
thought of them. So the real audience
was there and people imagined
conversations and rehearsed
conversations. So they had shadow
audiences. So I think the issues of
shadow audience and status go way back
beyond symbolic systems and beyond uh
syntax and semantics.
So does it
exacerbate or ameliate the fundamental
non-llinguistic game theory of
conformity conformity and group living?
>> Uh I think it's the root of it. I think
it's the it's the origin. It's where it
all came from.
>> But group group living was prior to
vocalization
though not necessarily prior to to um
pherommonal or stigmic communication.
>> Yeah, that's that's a very interesting
question whether that I mean whether
that actually preceded
language evolution.
In other words, in a chimpanzee group,
they are conscious of their own status.
Probably they know some of the chimp has
higher status than them. But I think
this all became exaggerated in humans
because of the sexual selection for
showing off intelligent. It became so
much more complicated because we added
intelligence to the mix as the thing
that was sexy and attractive and that
made it all so much more complicated.
H okay. Um
where do you think this relates to a
priori languages or to our sort of
current cognitive linguistically
informed use of language?
How do you how do you see
this
propositional
explication of the role of language in
cognition and evolution
re-entering
into human language use
as opposed to language being
um
a useful tool but not necessarily itself
theorized about
>> um not sure I get the question
>> like do you think this will lead us to
uh constructed languages
or to elaboration or simplification of
languages or some other way to think
about how media and different uh formats
of communication are used or or norms
around required or forbidden methods of
communication.
based upon a a grounded understanding of
what the consequences of those
violations of those norms would be.
>> Well, I I think um I I don't see much
future for synthetic languages used by
people, you know. I mean um people
develop language. languages evolve as in
the previous slide to be useful for
people and um so I don't see the
synthetic languages
uh will do anything except evolve to be
like ordinary languages
um am I answering the question probably
not
>> I I think I mean that that's kind of a
funny conclusion but yes the goal of a
of a constructed lang language would be
to become an ordinary one. And how would
you relate it to language of thought and
if we have the sessation whether we take
this in a more meditative direction or
not?
What is in the absence of
verbal or linguistic mental chatter?
What is the structure of thought that
occurs without language?
Great question. How
um
well you perhaps you should look at Mets
in his book to what he thinks goes on
when there's not language happening. But
I think we always have imag physical
imagination. We always can physically
imagine situations and run simulation
and work out what happens next. So
that's a component of thought which is
going on even when language is going on.
I think everyday thought is a mixture of
physically imagining things
and putting words around it.
And the physically imagining things
still goes on when you don't have words.
>> Physically meaning physically imagining
>> the situational and spatial awarenesses.
>> Spatial awareness. Yeah.
How would you think the analog wave or
spatial representations interface
mechanistically or or just cognitively
with that naming process? Is there a a
supervisor of that spatial wave that
names or is the wave become translated
into some describable process?
Well, if you say if you believe as I do
that, the basis of consciousness,
spatial consciousness is this wave in
the palamus, then that happens in all
higher animals and any higher animal can
take its spatial experience and it can
find things in the space around it and
classify them. You know, you can
classify here's an insect, here's a
flower, whatever. So that classification
into categories that are useful for the
animal has evolved into classification
into things that we name as human
speakers.
So it goes back to animals, but the
animal brain has always been able to
link the wave with classifications of
things that are useful to know about.
Okay, I'll I'll read some comments in
the chat and we can look at these and
and some of these other topics. I I I
really enjoy the Robert. you're you're
bringing a a huge amount of uh of
inquiry and and research to bear and it
just lightly touches on a lot of key
areas that that brings a consilience to
a lot of the cognitive and the
linguistic quest which is just it's the
water we swim in metaphorically
speaking.
Okay. Active bloomology wrote language
as cause of human affection. Please.
>> Affliction.
Is there possibly a connection with
speech being disembodied?
>> Speech being disembodied?
Um,
in what sense? Disembodied? I mean
um
uh
I I I struggle to find a connection
really. I mean speech is disembodied.
Is that referring to the fact words are
kind of arbitrary sequences of sounds
and not don't have any resemblance to
the things they're talking about?
I think if that's the question that
words are totally decoupled from their
meaning terms of the sound sequence has
nothing to do with the what the word
means.
Um
I think that feature of language arose
because we need so many words and we
need words for things which
there's no possible way in which the
sound can resemble the concept and so we
just need some arbitrary string of
sounds to represent some concept.
Um again I'm not I feel I'm not
answering the question here.
Yes, that reminds me of kind of
Schroinger's what is life and about the
quasi periodic crystal and about the way
that there there there has to be some
substrate
that has enough reuse and modularity to
allow recomposition.
But then that to the extent that those
compositions are meaningful and this is
also kind of explored in the girdlebach
the subunits do not have that type of
meaning. Letters mean things that words
can't, words me must do and mean things
that sentences can't. And and like they
they partition into this hierarchical
basian niche.
And uh so then that that
creates these smaller artifacts
which need to be taken in a Gestalt
context.
>> Yeah. They have to be arbitrary in some
way.
>> Yeah. And that that defies a sort of
reductionism. We don't we don't take a
magnifying glass and look deeper at at
the pixels on on the paper. Um but how
about this human sense of self is
secondhand and flawed. So we're having a
firsthand experience of that secondhand
flawed
concept. So what or what is the
firsthand
experience is the second hand
>> the firstand concept of self would be me
thinking about myself directly
I do this I do that and and therefore I
am that way or this way. The second hand
concept is me not thinking about me as
my own personal experience, but me
trying to imagine what other people
think of me and me trying to guess.
Does my bum look big in this these
trousers sort of thing. What do I look
like to other people? That's the
secondhand part of it. It's not my my
idea of me.
It's my idea of what other people are
thinking of me and why it's flawed. One
reason is that [clears throat]
I'm imagining what other people think of
me
when other people are actually not
thinking about me. They're just thinking
about themselves
and I'm also doing it by these quick
basian patterns pattern matching
[clears throat]
which are sometimes inaccurate. And
people's idea of themselves as we know
can be very inaccurate.
So that's why I say it's secondhand and
flawed.
So that's kind of like the thinking
through others other minds TTOM.
Um,
why is that
flawed
when we could also have a firsthand
experience that has false positive or
false negative assertions?
Well, it's secondhand that it's it's in
a mirror, the mirror of other people.
It's flawed in that when we learn these
patterns in conversation, the self
patterns, status patterns,
um we are only learning what we need to
carry on a conversation. If once we've
learned something good enough to carry
on a conversation with somebody, that's
it. Uh it needn't learn any anymore. But
that may not be an accurate view of what
they really think of us. We're
extrapolating from in conversation. We
can't have [clears throat] direct
evidence of what the other person's
thinking because they if we say
something wrong b they or something
that's based on an uh a misconception
they will correct us. But the shadow
audience in private thought can never
correct us.
So we can get away with errors. We can
apply status patterns that are just
wrong in private thought and nobody will
ever correct us. Whereas in public
conversation, people will sometimes
correct us.
>> Interesting because that shadow audience
can also be a sort of critical internal
commentary.
>> So it can make critical
>> it can drive that can drive that. Yeah,
I mean it can lead to internal conscious
experience of you can it's preconcious
it's preconcious pattern matching but it
can lead to conscious trying to um make
it better trying to work out what other
people will think of you.
But the conscious stuff is always going
so much slower than the preconscious
pattern matching. The pattern matching
is going at two or three patterns status
patterns per second. conscious thought
is going one new thought every 5
seconds.
>> Yeah, I'm very interested in that. Like
what kinds of
exercises or experiments
help us
get a look at that fine tooth gear
or that kind of splicing of the moment
that happens at the subsecond level. How
how do you how how over your life and
research have you explored that and how
how did it come to be the way that you
think of it now?
>> Well, I don't think we really have a
microscope to look at our own thinking
at the subsecond level. Um, so this is
kind of theoretical speculation. It's
saying how language works. I mean, I I
know that when I hear somebody speaking
at three words per second, I'm doing
three fast basin pattern matches per
second to understand what he's saying.
I'm doing more than that because I'm
trying out several other patterns which
don't make the cut, so to speak. So, I
know it happens, but I can't look at
myself internally and say what's
happening at the 1/5 of a second
interval.
Um, the only thing I can do towards that
is practice mindfulness when I slow down
some of this stuff and perhaps get some
other insights into what's going on.
Do you
>> I mean I think in mindfulness you do you
do experience life without without the
urge to do things and life without the
urge to change things and you can bring
insights out of that which are valuable
to you. this what happens. But um
no, there's no way of of putting a
microscope on your own thought.
How do you relate that to neuro
phenomenology and to cognitive science?
And what kinds of tools or what
apparatus
measurement or perturbation apparatuses
do you think would further this line?
Well, I mean in the lab we could do MRI
experiments or um to actually find out I
mean perhaps we could actually get an
experimental probe of basian pattern
matching of words in the lab and and see
these things happening externally in a
person in a scanner. But um that's a
speculation. We we're not very close to
that yet I think. Well, we see what
parts of the brain language is
happening. But um to get the detailed
patterns about how status patterns are
happening for instance would be um it's
possible but not happened yet I think.
Where do you see this
these research questions going or taking
you over the coming years for yourself
and for for the field like what what are
we seeking to reduce our uncertainty
about what would be the learning moments
and what what would be the utilities
>> um well firstly the learning moments
what are we trying to reduce our
uncertainty about I think we're still
trying to get a decent model of language
I think the world has been very confused
by chsian linguistics
which has introduced a load of red
herrings. Uh I think the picture of
cognitive linguistics needs to be
reinforced and I think in research terms
as I've tried to do in these talks you
need to extend cognitive linguistics
beyond syntax and semantics to do
pragmatics. I think we need to validate
a good model of pragmatics by
testing it against lots and lots of
pragmatic phenomena.
and building those models
computationally that work. And that's
what I'm going to be trying to do, build
a a working computational model of
pragmatics.
So, I think there's a lot we can do to
improve our theoretical understanding of
language.
Um,
now where was I going with that? Um, oh
yeah, in terms of the practical impact,
I think there is potentially huge
practical impact because there is so
much suffering and bad things happening
in the world as a result of these shadow
audiences and a result of status
patterns and mindfulness
does offer some relief from that. So I
think a better scientific understanding
of mindfulness might in time lead to
better ways of
learning it and teaching it and more
widespread mindfulness, more widespread
appreciation of why the big bad things
go wrong in the world.
And who knows we might eventually be
able to collaborate with each other
enough to solve problems like climate
change. So there are huge practical
implications if mindfulness is
um a way forward on
these afflictions of the human race.
Yeah, there's a lot there in the the
scale of coordination that different
communication and trust mechanisms
enable.
Um,
several of these pieces are about sexual
selection and about that sort of about
how even though the sexual environment
is natural, it still has selective
signatures
that can be distinguished from the
abiotic niche
with selection operating on it. And
I guess what where does that line take
us? Understanding that although language
helps us address these basic biotic
challenges,
it is also able to be harnessed by
mimemetic
or even
yeah transient
peacock
type dynamics or green green beard
dynamics.
all these different more evolutionary
subg games that exist.
Like, is is that our our faded condition
or would there be a way to
well I I mean I don't think uh
evolutionary time scales are of interest
here. In other words, evolutionary time
scales are at least thousands of years
before the human species changes in any
uh perceptible way. I think we got much
less time than that.
Um, I think we need to
understand how the human race shoots
itself in the foot repeatedly over the
next 50 or 100 years and start getting
an understanding of why we do that and
how we can do it less out into common
understanding, not esoteric scientific
understanding, much more widely in the
next hundred years so that people are
less beset. debt by these status issues
and tribalism and and group think and so
on and so forth in the general public.
The whole 9 billion people on the
planet, a large proportion of them
should be somehow see mindfulness as
less esoteric, less mystical and a
practical common sense thing to um
live better and more cooperatively.
I don't know how that's going to happen
or whether it's going to happen, but it
is a possibility.
>> In the chat,
what does modeling pragmatics with
others look like?
>> What does which pragmatics
>> what does
what does modeling pragmatics with
others look like? Like possibly what
what does that in practice?
What kinds of conversational games or
exercises or trainings or experiences
could help bring a fluency to to those
who are exploring what it means to to
model
pragmatics of language together?
>> Um h
>> how do people bring this into their
daily conversations? Is it uh
>> I don't think they do. I I think it's a
matter of understanding how we do daily
conversation, not trying to manipulate
that in any way. In other words, what we
do in conversation.
Um well, let me let me step back a bit.
What we do in conversation is a product
of this learning conditioning process
where we learn all these word patterns.
We learn status patterns. I think one
very important
change mechanism is to is really with
young children when they're learning
and maybe there are ways in which adults
can structure the environment just bring
children up better so that they don't
learn the harmful status patterns
and I don't think that that is in the
structure of conversations it's in
understanding where self-esteem comes
from, understanding how you give a child
space in which to learn about things and
not um
learn the harmful self-esteem patterns.
So, I think that is a tremendous
potential for progress if we understand
better how to bring up our children and
do so so they're more sane than we were.
I'm also sometimes struck by that with
like bringing cognitive science into
dayto-day,
but there isn't anything else to do or
bring in.
Any activity is going to fall into this
category.
It's more of a lens
that
helps us understand any kinds of speech
acts.
I I think that's right. It's a lens that
helps us understand rather than
manipulate or change.
languages about status is is still so
interesting to me as well because
seemingly apparently there are
expressions that don't relate to status.
Are those just accessory expressions
that are kind of like tributary kind of
corlary expressions that that don't
really arise from the main thrust? Or do
we translate even the status
personification, objectification,
ranking, judging onto even like well
this is my favorite
coin on the table? And it basically
applies status games to even objects.
>> Anything we can talk about can have
possible status reverberations in some
people who hear it. You know you you
can't
no sub I mean the basic idea is that
people have usually thought of language
as some kind of neutral medium harmless
medium and all benefits medium which we
use to talk about reality and it's
neutral and it doesn't bias our view of
reality.
What I'm saying is that
really it's so soaked in status as in
this slide. I'll come back to this slide
here. Language is so soaked in status
that more or less any sentence you say
um is going to bring in status issues in
some listeners and is going to
reverberate with them. And
more or less anything you say can even
when you're talking about some abstract
scientific topic if you're favoring a
scientific theory hypothesis which
somebody else has worked on a different
hypothesis that immediately reverberates
with their self-esteem. They don't like
it when different ideas challenge their
own.
Okay, in the chat. So, speech acts are
political.
Actually this slide that you have right
here, this relates to um sort of the
man as political animal and about the
distinction between zoo and bios
and um like zoology and biology
and about different um there's just a
lot of interesting etmology and theory
there that Agamin and others have
explored
about um the The zoo like zoologology
is this right column with the animal
layer and then the the layer of what is
added beyond that that makes you know
human the political animal.
>> Yeah. I mean I could have used the word
politics in many places in this talk.
Yeah. It comes in politics is just
status written large really.
Um, yeah. What are what are your next
moves or what what let's let's check in.
What is on your research portfolio?
We have the wave, the flies,
consciousness like how are you seeing
these different threads merging and
splitting right now?
Well, I think one important strand is to
merge the wave consciousness idea with
this model of language and and and I
think a lot may come out of that.
Um I would like to
um
sort of integrate this more with the FE
portfolio of ideas and if anybody is
interested in doing an FE because this
is I'm saying language is basian
inference and I'm saying that the wave
is a basian optimal model of
our physical surroundings and so they're
all very FE compatible and I would like
to do FE implementation of
if somebody who's more expert than I am
in FE techniques would care to
collaborate on it. So I think those are
important lines but integrating language
and consciousness I think is very
important because a part I haven't
talked about here is how we get
conscious of language meanings
and that all has to be done.
uh I think just
mechanizing the model of pragmatics,
producing a computer implementation that
does pragmatics and demonstrating the
steps of building up the common ground
and so on. That's an important topic. So
there's plenty going on.
Where would you say pherommonal
symbolic communication
would come into play
in reference to the insect neuroanatomy
or not?
Um, now I'm
currently looking at insect brain
anatomy in a very different way because
obviously they have they don't have
language or anything like it. They
probably do have consciousness. But um
what's happening on the insect brain
with me at the moment is I'm just
looking at the data on the fruitfly
connetoone and finding patterns which I
don't think have been seen before of
groups of neurons that act together what
I'm called partner neurons and this
um is just saying to me that there are
things about brains in general insect
brains or verteate brains
which are just much more complicated
than we think. I'm beginning to think
the old McCullik pits model of a neuron
where a neurons a kind of simple adding
machine
can't be the whole story only a tiny
part of the story. And I think insect
brains may help us because they're such
because they are smaller and more
examinable.
um they may help us explore that what
brains are really doing. I think the
neuron
if you think a neuron is just a mullic
pits neuron with hebian learning that
seems to me such a vastly oversimplified
picture what a neuron is but it can't be
right that's what I'm trying to look at
with the insect brains but that's a a
different topic really [snorts]
>> yeah oh well yeah a lot of cool things
with intracellular
computation dendritic trees and and when
you look at the morphology of some of
these neurons sounds
amazing in the insect brain. Um but they
do also have different songs
>> sometimes songs
>> like different stridulation
>> like language
it's what what would would you say that
it has to be
>> oral or could it be sequential
>> in it or does it have to even be
sequential even something like braille
I mean is the key aspect that is
I I I think we should just restrict the
word language to human language and and
we should use a different word like
signaling or something for what animals
do.
And insects certainly do signaling, but
um they've never had sexual selection
for for language ability. Never never
had to show off their intelligence to
other insects, I don't think.
What about uh sexual signaling with song
and dance and nest construction?
Oh yeah, that there's a huge amount of
that all over nature that people animals
learn courting rituals and courting
songs and and so on and that. But none
of those I think have got to the state
of human language of showing off.
Animals have to show off that they know
the code. They know how to dance or they
know how to sing a certain pattern of
songs, but they don't have to show off
that they're more intelligent. They can
compose these things um using
intelligence. I think that's the
specifically human thing which led to
our oversized brains.
So, what ways would you say people could
get involved or contribute or just how
do you take this from here?
Um, what I'm hoping to do is get the
pragmatics ideas more widely
appreciated.
Um,
and if anybody wants to pick those up
and do an FE implementation of them or
work with me on a general
implementation, that would be great. But
I I just want to get those ideas out
there because what I feel is that if I
present a unified theory of language,
that's too much to take in one bite
and people will say, "Oh, well, there's
too much there. Haven't got time to read
it." Whereas if I can concentrate just
on pragmatics, people might say, "Let's
have a look at this."
Just want to get the ideas out there.
Yeah, I I'll be really interested to see
that. and Elliot Murphy's work,
Similarities and Differences, and
Michael Walker and Hector Monrique and
their discussions of uh kind of the
cognitive niche and the communicative
niche that that led to theory of mind
type developments.
Um, but you brought up many interesting
areas and I I mean there's a lot to
H
>> how can how can we wordlessly or
wordfully integrate?
>> Let's just say that after this stream we
were going to reflect. Do we always
return to the same mindful attractor
with generic cues
to um
release or or evade linguistic naming?
Or is there a way to set an orientation
for a for let's just say material heard
during a lecture
that both
points towards the content that was
learned
but also doesn't stay within a
linguistic interior monologue rehearsal
setting.
That's huge questions there. Um
I I I come back to mindfulness and I
think a big part of mindfulness is being
mindful of the fact that you're not
mindful. Being aware of these patterns
dragging on you
and and that in a strange way leads to
more freedom from them. But it's it's
hugely difficult to summarize,
especially in words.
>> Do you feel like any of this has to do
with your name
being warden?
>> Well, it's an old Norman name means
guardian. I don't think
Very well. Very well.
Thank you, Robert. Um, looking forward
to how this proceeds and exploring the
insects and hearing more about
consciousness at the symposium.
>> Great. Many thanks, Dan.
>> See you.
>> Bye. See you.